Guide to the International Monitor Institute. Burma Videotapes, circa 1990-2002 RL.00605
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Burma Videotapes, circa 1990-2002, 287 videocassettes
  - Nobel Peace Prize Award Ceremony 1991, NTSC VHS [TRT 2:15:00] (Box 298, Video-cassette BU007)
    Smiling faces. LSD upsets proud people, twice demonetization triggers massive bankruptcy and subsequently the people's uprising. Army brutally responded, 42 killed.
    Justice at own hand, beheaded suspected military agents.
    State Law and Order Restoration Council (LORC) took over power and killed hundreds. Army said they were looters. Min Win said, "In front of US embassy, army from the roof shot at us." Thet Naing Aung said, "I saw a girl shot at leg; one nurse rushed to the girl but bullets hit both of them. I saw them both went dead still."
    All Burmese Students' Democratic Front (BSDF) is born. Zaw Oo said, "We protested peacefully but they shot us unarmed civilians. Arrested scores and female inmates raped."
    Soe Min, "We were asked to disperse but we refused. Then they shot at us. Many died; some of them were just passers-by."
    Ye Gaung, Journalist: "The socialist dream put us to the LSD. We want democracy. We will never get it in the presence of military government."
    Tanimsarim river bank Karen National Union (KNU) camp. Saw Lone: "One is brutality of the regime the other rumors of arriving foreign aid. New chapter in Burmese history. They now see what's going on."
    Myint Thein of All Burma Students' Democratic Front (ABSDF): "We will fight hand in hand with ethics." 4 Cuts.
    Than Minn Htun: "My daughter was weak. She fell when bullet hits her. But my son who was brushed by bullets did not die. They stabbed him, threw him and my daughter to the fire.
    Teak & black marketsources of KNU income.
    Manaplaw hospital.
    Bo Mya giving award to the disabled.
    A Boxing match.
    National Democratic Front.
    "I don't want to see more lives lost." Cho Cho Kyaw Nyein
    Preparation for election. Thakin Chit Maung. Heavy inflation.
    Khin Nyunt: "We don't restrict any party unless they operate under law."
    U Nu: "Government seems to be fair this time."
    National League for Democracy's (NLD) U Tin Oo (Thura Tin Oo) welcomed the election. Aung San Suu Kyi is Burma's Butto.
    Army is not sincere according to students. We fight for freedom with our way.
    Unwelcome peace talks.
    "Burmese are never our enemies," said Bo Mya.
    Breng Sang, Kachin Independence Army: "Peace is on the table, not on the battle field."
    Saw Lone: "People expect student to lead a change but they must move right."
  - ABC: Interview with Aung San Suu Kyi, NTSC Betacam SP [TRT 00:30:00] (2 copies) (Box 292 and 298, Video-cassette BU008)
    Produced by: AsiaWorks/ABC
    Network: ABC
    In July, 1995, Aung San Suu Kyi's appears for the first time in public since her release from house arrest.
    Outdoor speeches and Q& A session with the people.
    "Ethnic issues should be resolved. The State Law and Order Restoration Coucnils' (SLORC) cease fire was not a successful one because people still carry arms. When peace prevails there is no need for people to hold arms."
    Drug addiction is at a dangerous level. There is not enough evidence to conclude money laundering of drug sources. Suu Kyi is still organizing the National League for Democracy (NLD) and is not ready to go around the country. NLD is elected by people. Journalists want news. Ethnic issue has to be addressed democratically. Among Burmese there is a lack of trust.
    Supporters were waiting for Suu Kyi outside. As she emerged, people chanted, "Good Health to Daw Aung San Su Kyi! Good health to Uncle U Tin Oo & Uncle U Kyi Maung!"
    Q & A: Democracy is the truth and the appropriate ideology for everyone.The other side is dictatorship, which is very harmful to the people. There is a difference between the silence of fear and the rule of law. Pandit Neru's government should reveal truth and justice. Law and order are rules of discipline. The government must not ignore the will of the people.
    Suu Kyi explains the characteristics of being a good king. "A good king observes moral and spiritual leadership in a country. He does not give away truthfulness. He sacrifices. He does not lie nor trick the people. He always listens and analyzes the people. Opportunists around the king are often dangerous." Democracy is to respect the equitable right of every individual.
    A group of newsmen accompanied by U Kyi Maung and U Win Htein.
  - AsiaWorks: Edited Story Packages on Burma, No 1, NTSC Betacam SP [TRT 00:30:09] (2 copies) (Box 292, Video-cassette BU009)
    Produced by: AsiaWorks/Image Asia
    Composed of nine short segments on Burma's situation, 1995
    1.4 Min 10 Sec. Report on people's fear of Junta. Army guarded Aung San Suu Kyi's home. One general was quoted saying: "Suu Kyi tried to break the army apart. Army should assume power to prevent Burma from becoming like Bosnia Herzegovina"
    A brief appearance by Michael Aris.
    2.3 Min 19 Sec. State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC)'s Union Day Celebration; colorful ethnic costumes, people paying tribute to army. Tens of thousands of Karen and Rohingya refugees fled SLORC onslaught. Ethnic dancers seen saluting and paying tribute to army.
    3.4 Min 7 Sec.SLORC's preparation for Myanmar visit in year 1996. Win Htein training hotel staff. Report argues that with present pace of progress, to expect half a million tourists in a year is too much too soon.
    4.3 Min 32 Sec. First Credit Card issued at Myanmar Oriental Bank (MOB). Interview with Los Angeles-based Albert-Naing. People will be free from carrying cash in bulk. Report says the majority can not carry cash in bulk.
    5.3 Min 23 Sec. March 27 Military Day march. Interviewed army officer says army granted democracy in Burma but it must be Burma's own way that suits the people.
    6. 3 Min 15 Sec. Tachileik Border town - a boom town. At the edge of Golden Triangle, there were predawn attacks by Khunsa Mao Htai army. They shook the town with gunfire and motor shells. Civilians crossed the river to Thailand. SLORC rocket caused the entire compound to burn. Only 3 were captured and the rest escaped, leaving 600 people homeless.
    7. 4 Min. 58 Sec. A bridge over the river Moi (Thaung Yinn) was called Friendship Bridge. Maesot from Thailand side & Myawaddy from the other side. Burma stopped free passage and is on the Thailand side, put up barricade from Burma's half of the bridge, accusing Thailand of harboring the rebels. Business is stopped. Interview with business man Chaiwood.
    8.1 Min 56 Sec. Aung San Suu Kyi was released. New investments poured into hotel construction. Commercial hotel rooms are shown. Suu Kyi was warned to be careful.
    9.2 Min. 29 Sec. Aung San Suu Kyi's public speeches. SLORC conducted a Constitutional Convention which NLD said was a sham. SLORC tried to marginalizethe NLD and Suu Kyi.
  - AsiaWorks: Edited Story Packages on Burma, No 2, NTSC Betacam SP [TRT 00:45:00] (2 copies) (Box 292, Video-cassette BU010)
    Produced by: AsiaWorks/Heather Kally for ABC
    1- Economy in Burma, March 1995-06:00 min.
    2- Profile of Aung San Suu Kyi, December 1995- 07:30 min.
    3-Suu Kyi Primer, December 1995-04:12 min.
    4-Mae Sai, Thai-Burma Border, March 1996-03:04 min.
    5-AIDS in Burma, February 1996-02:38 min. NOTE: black is for graphic insert of report on AIDS in Burma.
    6-Crackdown on NLD, May 1996-02:10 min.
    7-NLD Congress, May 1996-02:30 min.
    8-NLD Congress, May 1996-03
  - AsiaWorks: Aung San Suu Kyi's Plea for Karen Refugees, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:03:15] (2 copies) (Box 299, Video-cassette BU011)
    Daw Aung San Suu Kyi in Karen, pleading to the world on behalf of Karen Refugees.
    Although the forefathers and founders of the republic have paved the way for national unity under equality to all ethnic minority, the plan has not materialized yet. Karen brothers fled because of the ravages of army persecution."We should end this violence and turn diversity into an enduring strength." Suu Kyi called for total unity among ethnic groups and the majority.
  - Human Rights Abuses/Newspaper Headlines/Torture, NTSC VHS [TRT 01:00:00] (3 copies) (Box 299, Video-cassette BU012)
    Produced by: Personal: HeatherKelly
    Miscellaneous Collection of human rights abuse in Burma and News Clips on Nobel Laureates' Visit to Burma -Thai Border refugee camps, February 1993:
    Picture 1, Floating bodies of porters
    2. Body with his hands tied behind his back
    3. Human wounds
    4. Karen Porter's fatal gunshot wound behind the ear
    5. Abandoned body of a porter
    6. Charred body with hands tied
    7. Land mine wound
    8. Karen female refugees
    9. Karen refugees' classroom
    10. Karen refugees w/ the reporters
    11. Burned-down camp site
    12. Burned-down camp site
    13. Camp site 3
    14. Bangkok Post February, 24, 1993
    Headlines: Laureates Mull More Burmese Sanctions
    15. Desmond Tu Tu's picture
    16. Dalai Lama
    17. News Clips on Burma by Thai local paper.
  - TV Myanmar: Documentary on State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC)'s rise to power in Burma, NTSC VHS [TRT 01:08:54] (2 copies) (Box 299, Video-cassette BU013)
    Produced by: TV Myanmar
    SLORC's justification for holding power and denial of the massacres in 1988. SLORC's version of the 1988 people's uprising: Communist party, foreign news agencies and human rights agencies were blamed as instruments in the civil and political unrest. Beheading those accused of poisoning the drinking water and attempt to sabotage the demonstration.
    Ohn Gyaw spoke: "The truth was overshadowed by the money making reports. No nation would tolerate such challenges andthey would absolutely deal with it the way we did. Changes were indeed already in place. The emergency Party Congress was held on the 23rd July 1988 when Ne Win announced his retirement and pushed for a referendum. But it was rejected. Sein Lwin was elected, but when he was unable to contain the disturbances he was replaced by Dr. Maung Maung. During those days, demonstrators caused massive destruction. Peace, order and the rule of law were challenged. Tatmadaw was the only organized and disciplined entity left in the country. It assumed power to stop the disintegration of the country."
    Burma Communist Party Politburo meeting was shown with detailed discussion translated into English.
    "Demonstrators demanded a multiparty democracy to which the government agreed. But the formation of an interim government was the communist party's agenda. The slogans used by the demonstrators were communist party slogans. In the video clip communist leaders discussed taking power by turning down the interim government. The conclusion was that the people's uprising was nothing but the Communist plan to assumepower. To make the situation worse, the news agencies abroad spread rumors and fabricated reports on Burma and her government. Some human rights agencies instigated with unrelated and irrelevant issues. Force was used to protect the government property and only a handful were killed or wounded, unlike what was put in the foreign reports. Brutal beheading scenes were shown but it is stated that foreign journalists only recorded the bad things. Those beheaded, according to the mob, were the residents of the government-sponsored housing projects who were paid to poison the drinking water by Ne Win's daughter Sanda Win.
    Due to the brutal acts committed by the mob and the plan of the communist party and foreign agitators with vested interests in Burma,the national sovereignty and security were in danger. So Tatmadaw is ready to sacrifice for the good of Burma. It formed SLORC and assumed power. Eventually, law and order were reinstalled. Tatmadaw successfully saved Burma.
  - ABC (Australian TV): Various Reports on Burma, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:29:00] (2 copies) (Box 299, Video-cassette BU014)
    Produced by: ABC/Marc Laban
    Miscellaneous footage of Burma's leaders' international and local activities (from June '95 to early 1997).
    Edited report by Marc Laban: Usual weekend crowd waited at the gate of Daw Aung San Su Kyi hoping to hear her speak. Press conference of Aung San Su Kyi after the NLD annual congress in which State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) was hit hard by the mass unrest: "National Convention could not satisfy the desire of the people so NLD withdrew its support."
    General was threatened. She was confronted by the army and was very careful about making more such meetings. But she was not intimidated and pledged more series of meetings.
    Brief scene of Asia Pacific Economic Cooperation meeting in 1995 November.
    Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN) Ministerial meeting at Brunei in August 1995. Ohn Gyaw visited Sultan's representative of Brunei presented Treaty of Amity & Cooperation for Southeast Asia.
    In December 1995, the ASEAN meeting - SLORC visited Thailand. General Than Shwe &Thai Deputy Prime Minister at flag ceremony.
    Thai Government Building SLORC: Khin Nyut, Tin Oo and a group with tense faces watched Than Shwe sign the agreement. Photo opportunity.
    Edited Report of Marc Laban on new market economy by SLORC 1995. There was planned construction of 32 story Shang Rhi La Hotelin preparation for the "Tour Myanmar '96."SLORC wants business & foreign investment.Col. Myint Lwin SLORC wants more business. Asian, U.S & European company representatives rushed in JVC's cocktail party. Financial sector was privatized. "Myanmar Oriental Bank provided credit cards. Burmese money was bulky with odd denominations like 45 Bills and 90 Kyat bills," said a report by Los Angeles-based Albert Naing, "Only 500 cards so far have been issued. Majority Burmese have no money. Political uncertainty and dissatisfaction prevails. It is hard for the economic goals to be achieved. Aung San Suu Kyi could make a change but she has been under house arrest. Democracy and prosperity are far away at present."
    Edited Report of Heather Kelly on the Asia Business News, December 1996: "Calls for democracy are still heard. Heavily armed soldiers present evidence of no sign of tolerance. Student's call for freedom was responded by batons and water cannons. Leaders were jailed.Students said they would go out again and win it."
    Edited Report by Heather Kelley on the Asia business News, January 1997: "Aung San Suu Kyi called for total boycott on Visit to Myanmar in '96. Some believed the presence of foreigners would help SLORC soften their stand. 50% annual increase in tourism was observed."
    Interview with Armen Shark who had business in Burma for 3 years
  - Asia Business News: Report on Burma, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:32:00] (2 copies) (Box 299, Video-cassette BU015)
    Produced by: Heather Kelly, Marc Laban, Asia Business News
    In Kyan Daw cemetery and the Karen refugees protest rally, Burmese students protested.
    Edited report by Jeannie Graham 1997: Jeannie Graham's Interview with Philippines Under Secretary for Foreign Affairs, with U Htein Oo, National Coalition Government of the Union of Burma (NCGUB) (the Exiled Government), and with Kmer Nation Party Representatives of the Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN), Oct. 1996
    Helen Kelly of Asia Business News: "Government ordered the main cemetery (180 acres Kyan Daw) to be relocated. Relatives had to dig out the dead bodies and transfer them - it was the second time in three years. Tamwe has been turned into an army patrol post. No religious groups were excluded from this relocation. Muslims refused while Jews requested some outside help.
    Helen Kelly interviewed the former British Ambassador Julian Heartland Swam who lobbied to stop the relocation. Government Official said "Yangon has changed and cemeteries once in outskirt are now in the center of the city."
    Helen Kelly of Asia Business News reported on the Hey Kalot refugee camp, the Karen refugee protests, the Karen National Union (KNU) military march. Mariam said: "We need help from bignations. "Wounded soldiers were seen in hospital.
    Burmese exiled students protest ASEAN's attempt to include State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) in the group.
    Dec. 1995, the ASEAN delegate arrived in Thailand. (Jeannie Graham)
    Dec. 1995, the Philippines Under Secretary for Foreign Affairs and the ASEAN delegates (Jeannie Graham) interviewed U Htein Win, the exiled Elected MP: "ASEAN should not include SLORC. The world should put sanctions on SLORC for ignoring the will of the people." (Jeannie Graham)
    Interviewed Rep. of Kmer Nation party: "If enemy has many friends, enemy becomes strong. As long as he has many supporters SLORC will not bow to the people." (Jeannie Graham)
    In October '96, Alternative ASEAN meeting at Chualalakorn University Bangkok, Thailand.
    People making banners & placards and Aung San Suu Kyi's Portrait.
  - AsiaWorks: Aung San Suu Kyi weekend speeches (1995 and May 1996); Part I, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:36:00] (2 copies) (Box 291, Video-cassette BU016)
    Produced by: NLD Information
    Network: AsiaWorks
    People waited patiently behind the wires put up by the State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC). Monks, nuns, the old and the young were there. Suu Kyi appeared as people chanted "Good health and long live."
    "It was not appropriate to beg for the things we have the right to have. We and the people stood firmly on for democracy. Everyone must participate in building our future."
    U Tin Oo spoke about the SLORC's arrests of National League for Democracy (NLD) members. The regime organized anti-NLD rallies.
    "Taste of freedom is so good and pleasant. No one wants to live chained. People want freedom."
    People waited in the rain as Suu Kyi appeared with Kamout and thanked the crowd for coming in spite of the bad weather. She then answered questions covering the education situation, SLORC's stance on it and democratic issues." If rule of law is not prevailed, economic changes will never be successful. Lawlessness is dictatorship where man rules over the law. Democracy is the rule of law. Disrespecting the election result is an insult to the entire public who participated in election. Rulers are responsible for the good as well as the misfortune of the people. They should have the courage to face it."
    An episode showing a bad king who was blamed for everything that happened in his kingdom. Continued Tape 17.
  - AsiaWorks: Aung San Suu Kyi's weekend speeches (1995 and 1996); Part II, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:30:00] (2 copies) (Box 291 and 299, Video-cassette BU017)
    The Bad Kings anecdote continued.
    Suu Kyi: "Democracy is the only way the bad rulers can be averted. The voice that sanction hurts the public is only the voice of the businessmen, not the public. Sanctions to State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) won't hurt the Burmese majority. An example is the sanctions on Iraq. They should be partial sanctions while allowing humanitarian sectors to operate."
    Response to Dr. Maung Maung's comment on spending three months to write the constitution: Now it has been 6 years. They are incapable of handling it properly. And six years has also passed since the election was successfully done, yet nothing has done towards democracy. People's will is as strong as ever. Economic changes will not alter the people's desire for democracy. The ASEAN stand is so wrong. Doing business with SLORC means involving in social political life of a country."
    Rain fell heavily.
    Brief appearance of U Kyi Maung.
  - AsiaWorks: National League for Democracy (NLD) Headquarters and Aung San Suu Kyi Appearances, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:31:00] (2 copies) (Box 299, Video-cassette BU018)
    Aung San Suu Kyi and U Aung Shwe met the journalists. Suu Kyi read the NLD press release of November 22, 1995." National Convention must be based on the foundation of democratic principles, the rule of law on basic human rights such as freedom of speech, freedom to worship, freedom of expression and association. The regime-sponsored National Convention has not operated in accordance with those principles. Delegates are hand-picked. Only 15.24% are elected. Speeches are censored. Decisions are made before presenting to the convention. There is no fixed timetable. State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) broke their words of the duty to write the constitution. It's the duty of those elected in their declaration in 1/90. NLD welcomes dialogues."
    Press Conference at NLD Headquarters, Rangoon: Aung San Suu Kyi's outdoor appearance with her EC Tin Oo, U Kyi Maung and U Aung Shwe.
    The Strand Hotel scene: Lt. Gen. Kyaw Ba and Col Myo Nyunt appeared on November 22, 1995.
    NLD is representing the people. It is their duty to protest the convention. We are in politics not to gain power, or sit in the prime minister's seat. We are in politics to bring democracy to Burma.
    Aung San Suu Kyi with U Tin Oo, U Kyi Maung, U Aung Shwe, and U Win Htein and the delegates in Pinn Nii Taik Pone.
    The new light to Myanmar Government is not a dictatorial one.
    Strand Hotel: Lt. Gen. Kyaw Ba and Col. Myo Nyunt were seen in front of Sule Pagoda.
  - AsiaWorks: National League for Democracy (NLD) and the leadership situation in 1996, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:32:00] (2 copies) (Box 291, Video-cassette BU019)
    On May 26, 1996, Burma held the first Series of NLD meetings to bring democracy. Delegates were in line to register.
    Union Solidarity and Development Association (USDA), the youth wing of State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) designed to harass NLD members and activities.
    News conference: In May 1996, 191 NLD members were arrested including U Win Htein and U Thein Tin. "The appointment of inviting to questions has to be done at mutually agreed time. They should not have been picked up in midnight and brought to the unknown destinations. It was arrest."
    "It was a great honor to receive the Australia Award - a big help to Burmese democracy. It is not the personal award. It is an award to entire struggle for democracy."
    "Arresting aides and Prime Ministers is SLORC's method of cutting branches from stem. But the stem sprouts faster. Constructive engagement does not work at all. The oppression condition is worse. The option of open dialogue is the ultimate choice. NLD is always open to it."
    On May 26, 1996 Burma has the first series of NLD meetings. Delegates were in lines to register.
    MC and chairman U Aung Shwe had the opening speech. Aung San Suu Kyi read NLD statement.
    "Six years have passed since the election was held and nothing has been done to go forward. Global family is closer than ever.Democracy is demanded to guarantee everyone's freedom from fear, people's security and livelihood, rule of law and end people's misery once and for all.NLD was elected to fulfill the will of the people."
    Continued in Tape 20.
  - AsiaWorks: Interview with Aung San Suu Kyi, 1996; Part I, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:45:00] (Box 291, Video-cassette BU020)
    Produced by: AsiaWorks, Images Asia
    English translation of the National League for Democracy (NLD) press release.
    Interview: The arrests are not totally unexpected. State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) has been nervous whenever NLD makes a move, even when it is a normal political activity. The response was based on the extent of their fear. Lt. Gen Kyaw Thein's comment was that there is no need for opposition. He doesn't understand the democracy.